This program is brought to you by
Stanford University.
All right, let's let's uh start by
talking about uh
the universe as it appears at different
distances from us
and a couple of ways of thinking about
it. Different distances also means
different times is a way to think about
it.
First of all,
put ourselves at the center
and then we can draw
surfaces around us
at
different
distances.
Literally now I mean distances, perhaps
measured in meters.
And we can ask what we see.
As long as we don't look too far
then the fact that we're looking
backward in time is not very important
and doesn't change things very much.
Uh
the universe 100 years ago was not very
different than it is today.
Uh the universe a year ago or
uh you know, whatever,
very little different.
So
you have to go out an appreciable
distance
before you discover the universe is
aging or that it is getting younger as
you look out.
And of course as it gets younger it gets
denser
meaning to say that early on the
universe was denser.
As it gets denser it tends to get
hotter.
If you look out sufficiently far
to the point where the universe was
or where the universe appears to have
been about as hot
as the surface of the sun.
Of course it doesn't look to us when we
actually look up in the sky that it
looks like the surface of the sun and
that's because of the red shift that all
the photons coming from that place where
the universe was as hot as the sun in
the process of being of being
transported to us
those photons are red shifted and
they're red shifted by roughly about a
thousand a factor of a thousand.
That effectively means that the
temperature
that we
would see in the sky is about a thousand
times lower
or it appears to be about a thousand
times lower than the actual temperature
that where those photons were being
emitted from. But if we forget about
that red shift and we just
you know, fold in the red shift into our
calculations
and ask how hot the universe was at
various places then there's some place
where it
becomes as hot just about as hot as the
surface of the sun.
That's the place where the universe
became opaque.
Um it became opaque because the atoms,
particularly the hydrogen atoms,
universe was mainly made out of hydrogen
and a bit of helium.
Uh the hydrogen was ionized at
temperatures higher than about a
thousand well about uh
uh few thousand degrees.
And so
out beyond some place there are not
atoms but ions and ions consist of
nuclei which basically means protons and
electrons. So there's lots of protons
around and lots of electrons. I'll draw
the electrons as crosses and they're
freely moving around. They're not bound
to each other.
Even if they accidentally got bound to
each other
the high temperatures out there
would cause collisions
the collisions being energetic
collisions between atoms and also
another thing which is out there is
photons.
Those photons are all around us but when
we go backward in time those photons
have shorter wavelength and the shorter
wavelength means that they're much more
energetic.
So what's going on out in the surface
out here is it's full of high energy not
very high energy photons but um
x-rays basically.
X-rays
x-ray photons
and there are more x-ray photons in fact
most of the particles out there are
these x-ray photons by a factor of about
10 to the eighth or something like that.
Most of the particles out there are
photons.
That's also true today. Most of the
particles in the universe are photons
but the photons are so low energy today
that they're not
a significant part of the energy of the
universe.
But at that time they were a significant
part of the energy of the universe so
it's also full of photons.
And if by accident an atom happened to
form, you know, an electron happened to
get trapped
uh very shortly it would be called would
collide with a photon and get reionized.
And so what's out there is mostly
ionized gas and ionized gas
the one thing that it's not is
transparent.
Ionized gas
uh is a electrical conductor.
Electrical conductors respond to
electric fields by sloshing back and
forth and re-emit radiation and
basically they're opaque. So out beyond
some distance here
the universe is opaque. It's it's it's
opaque
uh to us and so we can't see anything
behind that surface of last scattering.
The surface of last scattering is
the place like the surface of the sun
where you go from opaque to transparent
and it happens reasonably suddenly.
Uh
reasonably suddenly.
Basically when the
temperature cools down below the
ionization temperature of hydrogen the
universe becomes pretty clear and we can
see through it.
Uh there's some region here which is
hard to see and then inside it we begin
to see galaxies and so forth.
I want to go back a little bit further.
And of course going back and further
further is a bit conjectural and it's
conjectural because
it's conjectural but we can guess what
it's like on the basis of known laws of
physics.
Laws of physics here that we're talking
about are atomic physics. We know all
about atomic physics.
Uh we know a great deal more than just
atomic physics. We know nuclear physics.
We know particle physics. We can go a
fairly long way out.
I don't mean long in distance
necessarily although it is long in
distance but to higher temperatures and
um
pretty well guess what was out there.
So let's talk about what was out there.
Incidentally
the particles in here in addition to the
photons are mainly protons and
electrons.
Now the protons mean the nuclei of
hydrogen. There's also some helium
nuclei, alpha particles
and a few
deuterons
which are uh
an isotope of helium but basically just
very simple elements like hydrogen and a
little bit of helium
as far as nuclei
electrons freely moving around.
Now no antiprotons, no positrons or
practically no antiprotons, practically
no positrons.
Uh just ordinary matter. Pretty much.
Ordinary matter except ionized.
Now as we go out
we eventually come to a temperature
which is high enough
that when two photons collide
two photons collide. There's uh the
wiggly lines represent photons. The two
photons collide.
Normally you think of photons as not
things which collide. You think of
ordinary light. Light just passes
through light. But high energy photons
do collide with each other
and basically what happens is they
create electron-positron pairs.
What comes out of here
could be two photons again. In fact
photons might not even collide. They
might just go right through each other.
But with some
probability
a probability of about one in 10,000 or
something like that uh these photons can
create an electron
let's call it e minus. The minus stands
for the fact that the electron has
negative charge
and a positron
which means the antiparticle
of an electron.
A positron which we call e plus.
Positrons and electrons are very very
similar to each other.
They are practically identical with one
exception.
They have opposite charge.
They have the same mass, exactly the
same mass
and properties which are almost direct
reflections of each other. For example,
if you take two if two positrons they
will behave exactly the same way as two
electrons would behave except with
electrons being replaced by positrons
and so forth. Almost exactly, not quite.
So, if you go back far enough,
now this will not happen with ordinary
light and the reason that
the light in this room or the light the
colliding light between the two bulbs up
there,
the reason is that the photons don't
have enough energy.
The energy of these two electrons, even
if the electrons were standing
absolutely at still,
if they had no motion at all, the energy
would be twice two two because there are
two of them times the mass of the
electron times the speed of light
squared.
Now, that's a significant amount of
energy. It's a lot more energy
than photons, for example, from the sun.
Two photons from the sun have energies
much much less than that.
Thousands and thousands of times less
than that. So, two photons colliding,
for example, from up from two different
stars will not have nearly enough energy
to do that. But as the temperature goes
up, as the universe
gets more and more dense going backward
in time, the photons become shorter and
shorter wavelength and eventually out
somewheres or at some very early time,
the universe was hot enough that
photons, when they collide, make
electron positron pairs. Electron
positrons can collide with each other
and make photons. Exactly the inverse
reaction can happen.
If you were to take a pot of material at
that temperature, you would have
reactions similar to chemical reactions
except the chemicals now would be
replaced by particles
and the chem nature of the chemical
reactions would be photon pairs become
electron positron pairs, electron
positron pairs can collide. In fact,
this positron over here can collide with
some other electron over here, make more
photons. And eventually if the system if
the pot is allowed to just sit there for
a long enough time, it will come to a
thermal equilibrium. And in that thermal
equilibrium, there will be a certain
ratio of photons to electrons and
positrons. The number of electrons and
positrons, you would think if if we
really really started
with no electrons and positrons to begin
with. Now, that's of course not
accurate. There are electrons in our
universe. But in fact, the electrons are
very very dilute compared with the
photons.
There's approximately 10 to the ninth
photons in the universe for every
electron. So, let's ignore the electrons
which are there to begin with. But as we
go backward, electrons get manufactured
by this pair production process
and so that in the early universe,
they're the only way they can be
manufactured in this way is to
manufacture both a positron and an
electron at the same time. So, apart
from this little bit of excess of
electrons that's presently here now, as
we go backward, we come to a time when
the universe had equal amounts of
electrons and positrons
or almost equal amounts of electrons and
positrons
at some temperature. Um
At first, first means at temperatures
which are not too high,
there will be more photons than
electrons and positrons. Why is that?
Well,
if we lower the temperature down below
where the photons have enough energy for
this, there won't be any electrons and
positrons.
So, it stands to reason if we raise the
temperature a little bit, just above the
threshold for making a few electrons and
positrons, there will be mostly photons
with a few electrons and positrons. But
as the temperature heats up and what
what this has to do with is the fact
that the photo that the electrons have
mass and the photons don't.
Photons have no mass, electrons have
mass. Electrons have some internal
energy due to their mass, photons don't.
But as you heat it up higher and higher,
the kinetic energy of the electrons
becomes much much larger than their mc
squared energy and the mc squared is not
important. So, eventually when the
temperature gets
much above the threshold for creating
electron positron pairs, uh electrons
and positrons, their mass is not
important.
The photons have no mass. Electrons,
positrons, and photons become
energetically very similar to each
other.
And all of a sudden, not all of a
sudden, but at that point, the number of
electrons and positrons, the density of
them, is about the same as the number of
photons.
Roughly speaking,
uh electrons, photons, and positrons all
have the same density and they're all
colliding around like mad. This is a
very very dense soup of
of charged particles. But what about the
protons?
The protons are still present.
Incidentally, they are
they're rather dense by now. Um
Millions of times denser than they are
in
in this room. They're very dense, the
protons. But there is not yet enough
thermal energy to be able to create
protons and antiprotons for for either
photons to collide and create protons
and antiprotons or electrons and
positrons to collide.
Why not? Well, it's because the energy
of a proton is m proton c squared
and that's about 2,000 times larger
than the energy of an of than the mass
of an electron. The mass of a proton is
about 2,000 times larger than a
electron. If you want to create a proton
and an antiproton,
you would need at least that much
energy.
So, as you go back, the universe
contracts in
in the sense of going backward in time,
universe contracts, gets hotter and
hotter and hotter and eventually it
rises to the threshold
where it becomes hot enough that the
particles can create proton antiproton
pairs.
And so this dense soup now becomes a
soup of photons, electrons, positrons,
protons, and antiprotons.
But
that's not really quite accurate.
And the reason No, it's it's not it's
it's more or less accurate. It's more or
less accurate. Incidentally, the
the number of protons in the universe is
about not about. As far as we know, is
the same as the number of electrons
because the universe is electrically
neutral.
There's no net charge in the universe.
So, the universe is electrically
neutral. And if it's electrically
neutral, it must mean there's as many
positively charged particles as
negative. The only thing around today
are protons and electrons.
And so only charged particles around
today are electrons and protons. So, the
number of electrons and the number of
protons is the same today.
But of course, once these positrons got
into the act, there were a lot more
electrons and positrons than there were
protons. But now we keep heating it up.
We keep heating it up.
What happens is not that we really
create large numbers of protons and
antiprotons,
but very shortly, by the time we get to
the energy needed to create protons and
antiprotons, there's also enough energy
to smash the protons into quarks.
Into quarks. And so
by the time you get to the energy or the
temperatures where protons and
antiprotons
become significant in this soup, really
what you have is quarks. Three quarks
for every proton.
Three antiquarks for every antiproton.
And basically they kind of the kind of
reaction that can take place, I'll just
draw you some simple diagrams that that
show you what kind of reactions can take
place.
The simplest one is an electron and a
positron come together. E plus and E
minus.
They create a photon.
That photon very quickly becomes
something else. It becomes a quark and
an antiquark. Q, that stands for quark.
Could be a positively charged quark and
a negatively charged quark.
There are in fact several different
kinds of quarks.
There are quarks with charges are 1/3 of
the electron charge. There are quarks of
charge of 2/3, but I don't want now to
get into the
into the particle physics of quarks.
The main thing is that the soup becomes
a soup not only of
electrons, positrons, and protons, the
protons are replaced by quarks
and in addition lots and lots of
antiquarks.
Almost as many quarks antiquarks as
quarks.
And so if we go back far enough
we Yeah.
Mesons are made out of quarks.
Once the temperature gets high enough to
to shatter a proton that also shatters
the mesons.
Now there's one more constituent There's
other There are other particles there
too. There are neutrinos
uh
and all sorts of particles.
Also gluons. What are gluons? Gluons are
very much like photons but they're the
things which are involved in holding
quarks together. So there's all kinds of
garbage. I mean all it's it's it's a hot
soup of
all of the particles that we normally
consider in atomic physics and in
nuclear physics.
Okay?
That's when the temperature gets to be
hot enough for
uh
for protons to be dis- dissociated.
If you ask me in in in degrees how hot
that is, I will have to think for a
while.
Uh
ask me later. I will we can work it out.
But
at some temperature this begins to
happen.
Now Yeah. So this would be hotter than
say inside a star.
Yes, this is hotter than inside a star,
definitely. Inside a star
uh there are no
anti-
particles for the most part, right?
So there aren't even positrons with any
abundance inside stars, yeah. So so the
sequence is going backwards in time,
right? Yeah. So so the real sequence is
the other way around. Yeah, the real
sequence is the other way around. That's
what I But I want to get to I want to go
back to a starting point and then
discuss how it happened that the
All right. So
if you get things hot enough
there are going There's going to be a
huge density of
particles and antiparticles.
The particles and the antiparticles will
occur in pairs like this, so there will
be an equal abundance
almost
essentially an equal abundance
of positrons and electrons on the one
hand and almost equal abundance of
quarks and antiquarks.
In fact, if we go back
sufficiently far
uh
then the universe contains
more or less equal abundances of every
kind of particle and its antiparticle.
It starts out It's electrically neutral
because it's electrically neutral today.
Incidentally, there's kind of an
interesting reason why the universe is
uh
or a simple way of thinking about the
fact that the universe is electrically
neutral.
If the universe is closed is closed and
bounded, in other words, if it has the
shape of a sphere, a three-sphere, not a
two-sphere
but if it has the shape of a sphere,
just think about this for a moment.
Let's use as our model of the universe a
two-dimensional sphere, the surface of a
balloon.
Now electrically charged particles
put out lines of force. Those lines of
force are the electric field. So if I
put an electrically charged particle,
let's let's begin with flat space.
Here's flat space.
And let's put a positively charged
particle in.
Electric lines of force go out away from
that uh particle.
And those electric lines of force are
simply the electric field or a way of
representing
describing or representing the electric
field of the charged particle.
But
it's useful graphically to just think of
it as lines of force. And the lines of
force neither begin nor end except at
charged particles.
Okay?
What law of physics is involved in
saying the lines of force never end
except at charged particles?
Well, it is Maxwell's equations but it
goes back a little to something a little
simpler than Maxwell's equations. It's
the Coulomb force, the one over r
squared force law.
The one over r squared force law
is the rule that says that is equivalent
to the rule that says that the lines of
force never end except on charged
particles.
Uh
Positive charged particles put out lines
of force, negative charged particles
suck in lines of
lines of force.
Now that's fine.
But supposing we lived in a world which
was this closed and bounded spherical
world.
Supposing we put a charged particle into
it.
Let's put the charged particle over
here.
Then the lines of force go out.
But they don't have anywhere to escape
to.
What happens to that? It's mapped.
It just goes around forever?
Well, they don't move. I mean they're
they're they don't They they can't go
around
No, they don't go around forever.
They simply refocus on the other end of
the sphere.
On the other pole. Supposing For
example, supposing we put a positively
charged particle at the North Pole of
the sphere.
Turn this up so that it's the North Pole
of the sphere.
Then they simply refocus at the South
Pole of the sphere.
I don't know how to draw that. They
refocus at the at the
at the other end of the sphere. But
refocusing means that the lines of flux
which the lines of force which flow
outward from the positive charge over
here
necessarily converge
at the antipode.
And what would that be if this were a
positive charge?
It'd be a negative charge.
All right? So in a closed and bounded
universe, you can't have a net charge.
If you're saying if there was no
negative charge there, there would be
one there.
If there was no negative charge there,
there would be that one there.
Right.
Right. This is where the lines of
flux converge. All right. But really
charged particles are charged particles,
so you can ask what kind of charged
particle would be there. The answer is
any kind of particle with the opposite
charge. So if this were a proton, this
could be an antiproton or it could be an
electron. The only rule is
that every plus charge has to match or
the number of plus charges and the
number of minus charges have to match.
In other words, in a closed and bounded
universe
the net charge must be
zero.
Now it's not clear that we live in a
closed and bounded universe, but I just
point this out to you as a as a sort of
mnemonic
for the fact that
the net charge of the universe
is zero
or at least it looks to be zero. Any
place where we find positive charges, we
find negative charges and we don't find
any large-scale concentrations of
positive or negative charge. They seem
to cancel out pretty well. Okay. So
Isn't the fact that we can see the
cosmic the CMB evidence of generally
transparent space?
Uh
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah, it's That's right. I mean it
That's right. They can't Yeah.
But the the charge neutrality is much
better than that.
The charge neutrality is much better
than just the fact that the universe
looks pretty transparent.
Uh
Anyway, it's electrically neutral.
That of course does not mean that the
number of protons is the same as the
number of antiprotons. It means the
number of protons plus positrons plus
all other positively charged particles
is the same as the number of the
opposite
negatively charged particles.
All right. So we started out with a
universe with a very started out or at
least sometime in the remote past, as
far back as we can trace
using the known laws of physics and
maybe even going a little bit past the
known laws of physics
we come to some stage where the universe
was extremely hot.
How hot? Hot enough that
um
you name any
experiment that's ever been done at a
particle accelerator the universe was
hot enough to have had particles in it
whose energy was at least that high.
All right? Uh that means pretty hot.
At that time
the number of
electrons or the the number of electrons
and positrons was about the same as each
other.
The number of quarks and antiquarks were
about the same as each other.
Uh and there was not only charge
neutrality
but Now I'm telling you empirical facts.
This is not obvious, but I'm going to
tell you what the empirical fact is.
That uh
Well
the There is theory.
The theory says
that very early in the universe it was
and it was when it was hot, it's hot
enough to have an abundance of both
particles and antiparticles
because these collisions between photons
and other things create particles and
antiparticles. All right. Let's suppose
that the universe started in a way which
was symmetric between particles and
antiparticles.
Let's suppose it started
exactly with the same number of
electrons as positrons,
the same number of quarks as antiquarks.
And in fact, as I said, quarks come in
different varieties. So, for each
variety of quark, let's suppose the
numbers were symmetric between particles
and antiparticles.
The reason that this is an interesting
conjecture
is because the laws of physics are
pretty much symmetrical, not quite,
between particles and antiparticles,
almost symmetrical,
to rather high precision.
Um a positron behaves the same way as an
electron does.
Uh as I said, I keep saying over and
over again, not quite, and it's true
that it's not quite.
And that symmetry, that symmetry between
particles and antiparticles, between
plus charges and minus charges, has a
name. It's called charge conjugation
symmetry.
It's the interchange of every particle
with its antiparticle.
Take all particles and replace them by
their antiparticles,
and that is a symmetry of nature,
which I will modify that statement in a
little while.
But,
if it were true,
you might say, why on Earth did the
universe not start out with an equal
abundance of
charged particles of the positive type
and the negative type, or better yet,
why didn't it have an equal abundance of
quarks and antiquarks?
Or did it have an equal abundance of
Let's suppose that it did for a minute.
Quarks and antiquarks, in your
imagination, you can replace that with
protons and antiprotons.
Uh protons and antiprotons are a good
stand-in for quarks and antiquarks. So,
for our purposes right now, we don't
really need to think about quarks. We
can think about protons and antiprotons.
Early early on, let's suppose for a
minute that the symmetry of nature under
reflection, replacing particles by
antiparticles, was actually a symmetry
of the universe. That the universe was
like that. As many positrons as
electrons, as many quarks as anti or as
many protons as antiprotons. And then
the universe started to cool.
What happened as it started to cool?
What would happen as it started to cool?
Eventually, it would cool down to the
point where the temperature was not hot
enough
for photons to collide and make protons
and antiprotons.
It might still be hot enough to make
positrons and anti electrons and
positrons, but not hot enough so that
when photons or other part or electrons
and positrons collide, not hot enough
uh to be able to provide
a large energy necessary to make protons
and antiprotons.
Then something will begin to happen. The
protons and the antiprotons can collide
with each other and create photons. The
photons have no mass. There's no problem
with with turning a proton and an
antiproton when they collide into
photons, but the photons simply don't
have enough Oh, and then of course,
a proton and antiproton collide, make
some photons.
The photons, of course, have enough
energy that they could convert back to
protons and antiprotons cuz they have
the same energy that they started the
proton and antiproton become photon two
photons. But then the universe expands a
little bit. What happens to the photons?
The photons lower their energy a little
bit because they get stretched. And when
the universe has expanded a little bit,
all of a sudden those photons no longer
have enough energy to be able to create
the protons and the antiprotons.
So, it becomes a sort of one-way street,
protons antiprotons colliding,
making photons, a little bit of
expansion sucks the energy out of the
photons, not enough energy to collide
and make protons and antiprotons, so
there's a one-way flow sort of
protons antiprotons,
the photons and electrons and positrons.
All right.
All right. We start depleting
the protons and antiprotons, and the
temperature continues to get lower
because of the expansion of the
universe.
And eventually, it goes down to the
temperature
where the photons
can no longer create electrons and
positrons.
That's a very high temperature, much
much higher than the interior of the
sun, but much much lower than
temperatures associated with protons and
antiprotons.
And all of a sudden, the same thing
happens.
Photons collide.
Sorry. Electrons and positrons collide
and make photons. Universe expands a
little bit. Photon energies are
diminished. Not enough energy to recycle
back to make electrons and positrons.
So, the electrons and the positrons
start
being eliminated in pairs.
The expansion of the universe
is relatively slow.
It's fairly slow compared to the rates
of collisions
and other microscopic things going on.
Universe is a slowly expanding pot of
stuff.
And it's mostly in equilibrium. It's
It's expanding slow enough that things
stay pretty much in thermal equilibrium,
except slowly decreasing in temperature.
What would happen under those
circumstances?
circumstances
is essentially all of the protons and
antiprotons would disappear.
They would disappear because they would
annihilate. Whenever a proton found an
antiproton,
they would And remember, this soup is
very very dense.
They would annihilate and form a pair of
photons. The electrons and positrons
would do the same thing, and eventually
all you would have left would be
photons.
Unless,
for some reason, let's say unknown at
present, there was a slight excess, or
perhaps a large excess,
of protons over antiprotons. Supposing
that in the beginning, for whatever
reason, that protons outnumbered
antiprotons two to one.
All right. So, for every uh for every
100 protons, there was only 50
antiprotons.
What would happen? Well, the 50
antiprotons
would find 50 protons to annihilate
with,
but there would be no way to get rid of
the remaining 50 protons that didn't
have partners. So, they would stick
around.
They would stick around and continue to
be there, and you couldn't get rid of
them. Why can't you get rid of them?
Because they can't find partners to
annihilate with.
Uh
same thing with the electrons and
positrons. Since the world is
electrically neutral, if it had more
protons than antiprotons, it would have
to have more electrons than anti
electrons and positrons to compensate.
But, exactly the same thing would happen
to the electrons. Now, there would be
what? 100 electrons
for every Sorry.
For
every 100 electrons, there would be 50
positrons.
The end these things would collide, find
each other, and you would be left over
with 50 electrons and 50 protons. Okay.
Well, that's logic is okay. That logic
is fine.
But, what would happen to the energy
of the particles that annihilated?
It would become photons.
Now, to a good approximation, the way
the universe is expanding is is called
adiabatic. It means slowly.
It expands slowly.
And for reasons that have to do with
thermodynamics, much more with
thermodynamics and statistical mechanics
than with particle physics,
the net number of particles doesn't
change very much with time. When an
electron and a positron collide to
annihilate, they tend to turn into two
pho- two photons.
So, as the time goes on,
this is really the really correct
statement is that the entropy of the
universe doesn't change as long as it's
expanding slowly. Slowly means the word
is adiabatically. As long as it's
expanding slowly,
uh the entropy of the universe doesn't
change. But, entropy can be translated
into number of particles. It's
essentially the same thing. So, the
number of particles doesn't change,
which means that
the electrons and positrons which
annihilated and the protons and
antiprotons are annihilated were
basically replaced by photons.
So,
the upshot is we can count today
how many particles
there were
at a much, much earlier time
uh by simply counting the number of
photons.
The number of photons and remember,
almost all particles in the universe are
photons. We can count the number of
photons.
And here's what we find. We find that
the number of photons in the universe
the number of photons in the universe is
about 10 to the 10th. Somewhere is
between 10 to the 10th and 10 to the 9th
times bigger than the number of either
electrons or protons.
So, for every electron and proton in the
universe today,
there are something like 10 to the 10th
photons.
That means if we go backward in time to
the time when everything was in a in
this hot soup and there were more or
less equal number of every kind of
particle and antiparticle,
it means that
for every
proton and antiproton, no, not for every
proton.
For every 10 to the 9th protons and
antiprotons, there was one extra proton.
All right? So, there was a terribly tiny
imbalance
between
particles and antiparticles
that seems to trace back practically to
the very beginning of the universe.
How do we know that it was such a tiny
imbalance? Because we look today and we
say all the particles which annihilated
turned into photons. So, now we look
today, how many photons are there for
every proton? And the answer is about 10
to the 10th or 10 to the 9th or
somewhere in there.
That means at early times
that the imbalance between particles and
antiparticles was only about one in a
billion.
Roughly one in a billion
uh extra protons for every
proton-antiproton pair.
Now, it's a good thing that there was
that little imbalance because if there
wasn't that little imbalance, there
would be no atoms. There would be
everything would have annihilated. Yeah.
Don't you look at it slightly
differently in the sense that let's say
you started with equal
on everything and statistically you
could say the probability
uh when it cools
that the probability of creating a
proton is 10 to the minus 9.
Rather than I mean, you know, there you
have these collisions and then it cools
this you're not stopping making the
collisions anymore. Yeah.
Um yeah, we're we're we're coming to
that. That's where we're going.
Right.
You're saying you're asking how do we
know that as it cooled that protons
weren't made? How do we know that the
only thing that happened was
annihilation? All right. Now, I'll I'll
I'll come to that. Um
in order for a protons to be created in
the process during the process of
cooling,
uh let's say as you say, let's suppose
there was equal number of protons and
antiprotons.
Where is that where are those protons
going? Where is that extra proton going
to come from? We have to create an extra
proton.
Now, to create an extra proton in order
to keep electrically neutral, we also
have to create a electron.
So, we start out with a world with equal
number of
electrons and positrons, protons and
antiprotons,
electrically neutral, but also neutral
with respect to particles and
antiparticles.
And now we want to make an extra proton.
So, an extra proton, we want some
reaction where a proton comes out,
but something else has to come out with
it because of electric charge, and that
would have to be an electron.
Or some other negatively charged
particle, but for simplicity, let's just
say like
where did the mass for these come from?
Let's say it came from a pair of photons
colliding.
Well, the only problem with this
is the standard rules of elementary
particles.
The standard model of elementary
particles does not contain such a
process. It does not contain any process
where the net number Now, I'm talking
about the standard model of particle
physics. Standard model of particle
physics means standard thing that the
that we know from laboratory physics and
not extensions that the that may or may
not be turn out to be correct in the
future.
The standard model which describes
particle physics very well
up to
um
energies of a thousand times the mass of
a proton,
contains no processes that involve
protons or could create protons that
don't at the same time create an
antiproton. This is called baryon number
conservation.
Baryon numbers for our purposes is
basically the number of protons. You can
add in neutrons. Protons and neutrons
are very similar to each other.
Uh the number of protons and neutrons,
protons plus neutrons minus the number
of antiprotons plus antineutrons.
That number is conserved in the standard
model of particle physics. That means
you cannot create a
proton without creating an antiproton.
And and this is not electric charge.
This process here
is perfectly good for electric charge,
one proton and one electron,
but it violates one of the rules
uh
empirical rules, entirely empirical,
that you can't create a proton without
creating an antiproton at the same time.
I might add that the same rule or the
same physics tells you that you can't
create an electron without creating a
positron.
Now, as I said, this is not the
conservation of electric charge
because as far as electric charge goes,
a proton and an electron together are
electrically neutral. It's the
conservation of baryon number.
Conservation of the net number of
protons minus antiprotons.
And neutrons and antineutrons.
So, the standard laws of particle
physics do not allow as you cool down to
create an excess of protons. Now, I
think that's the question you asked. Is
it
Uh
well, I'm not sure.
Right. You asked me how do I know that
as it cooled down that the excess didn't
didn't develop?
And what I'm saying is that the rules of
elementary particle physics do not
elementary particle physics
up to
or down to distance scales a thousand
times or 10,000 times smaller than a
proton, do not contain any processes
which would allow an imbalance
uh to to develop.
Okay?
Now, what does that really mean? That
doesn't mean that in cooling down from
some exceedingly high temperature,
this imbalance could not have developed
spontaneously. What it means is once the
temperature gets down low enough
to where we know the rules, where the
energies of collisions are low enough
that we know the rules of particle
physics, that there are no processes
at those energies, at those temperatures
and lower, that can do what you want.
But,
of course, we are always acting to some
extent in a sea of ignorance where we
don't know what physics is like at yet
smaller distances and higher
temperatures and higher energies.
So, one speculation
which is
I would say
I would say it's speculative. I would
also say there's almost complete
consensus among
cosmologists, experimental physicists,
theoretical physicists, almost
everybody,
is that in fact the universe did really
start neutral.
Now, why is it why should there be such
consensus for something we know nothing
about?
Hard to answer.
Hard to answer. But, it does seem a
little bit odd. If you go back early
enough,
you really do want where did this one
part in 10 to the 10th come from? That's
a very odd thing. One part in 10 to the
10th
is a very odd thing. It sort of makes
you want to believe that perhaps the
universe had as many protons as
antiprotons to begin with,
as many as electrons as positrons to
begin with, and that as you say, that as
it cooled, something caused it
to be biased in one direction to create
a few extra protons and a few extra
electrons. That is widely believed,
but you have to go back to times and
temperatures which were above the
temperatures where particle physics has
been
successfully
tested, shall we say, where the standard
model has been successfully tested.
So,
what does it take?
I just want to talk a little bit about
your question. What does it take in the
way of changes in particle physics
or the way in the in the rules of
particle physics
to allow a universe which started
with the number of protons equaling the
number of antiprotons.
Now, I should say,
when I say protons,
I mean things with I mean a collection
of objects that includes neutrons,
protons, and other objects called
baryons.
But, let's simplify the story to just
protons.
Let's start not that a proton equals an
antiproton. The bar, incidentally,
stands for anti.
I don't mean that a proton is the same
as an antiproton. That's nonsense. They
have opposite charge. I mean
that the number of protons, let's call
it the number of protons equal the
number of antiprotons.
Supposing we start that way in the very,
very early universe. Incidentally, these
speculations were first made by Andrei
Sakharov in the Soviet Union
uh in about 1967. They were totally
unknown in the West. Nobody knew about
them.
And they were rediscovered actually by
Dimopoulos and myself around 1980, 13
years later.
And the subject is called baryogenesis.
Genesis means the birth of and baryo
here stands for baryon number, which
means proton number, and so forth. All
right. So, the idea is, first of all,
the laws of particle physics
must violate at some level, at some high
temperature, and at some high energy, it
must violate the rule that protons
cannot be created without antiprotons.
In other words, it must violate a rule
called the conservation
of baryon number.
The conservation of baryon number is
basically the conservation of the number
of protons minus antiprotons.
That's the
the conservation of that quantity in the
standard model of particle physics is a
known experimental and theoretical fact,
the conservation of it.
But, if you go back to earlier times
when the energies were higher, when the
distances were smaller, when we go
beyond what we really know,
there's no reason why this law of
conservation of baryons or baryon number
must be true. In fact,
we believe it's probably not true.
There's very, very strong reason to
believe a number of grounds
that the number of protons minus
antiprotons can change. Now,
the electric charge cannot change. So,
that means every time a new proton is
created without an antiproton, it must
go together with an electron being
created. That's okay.
We don't mind that. The world is
electrically neutral.
But, the first condition
for a theory
which starts out with equal abundance of
particles and antiparticles, the first
condition for it to get shifted a little
bit
is violation
condition number one.
Violation
of the conservation
of baryon number.
I'm writing down the three conditions
that Sakharov himself wrote down and
that Dimopoulos and I rediscovered
independently
and which are generally
almost complete consensus about about
this.
That's number one, that the laws of
physics must allow processes
such as this where a pair of photons can
come together and make a proton and an
electron. It would require a new set of
interactions, a new set of phenomena
which can only happen at energies so
high that we haven't yet seen them in
accelerators.
So, that's number one, violation of the
conservation of baryon number.
Now, number two.
All right. Let's suppose there was a
violation of the of the conservation of
baryon number.
Uh let me give you an example of a
conservation law.
Conservation of position, my position.
Well, of course, this is not a
conservation law, but let's just suppose
for a minute it was. That would mean I
can't move.
All right? My conservation of my
location would literally mean I can't
move.
Now, I could violate I could imagine
that that's a law of physics, and then I
could imagine a small violation of it. A
small violation of it would mean I can
move a little bit,
maybe slowly.
But, it wouldn't necessarily say that I
can only move to the left. That's my
left, your right.
It might say that I can move a little
bit and change my position,
but offhand, perhaps equally likely to
the left or the right.
So, a conservation law can be violated,
but in a way which doesn't bias either
more protons or more antiprotons. It
simply allows In other words, for
example,
there could be a process in nature like
this, and there could be another process
in nature
the reflection of it where all particles
are replaced by their antiparticles.
This would become antiproton
and positron.
You might think if this could happen,
this could happen.
That would mean that
the conservation law is violated, but
it's not biased in a particular
direction.
It could increase the number of protons
or increase the number of antiprotons.
Then both kinds of things might be going
on. Over here, a proton might be
created. Over here, an antiproton might
be created. And obviously, on the
average,
uh
there would be no biasing, and on the
average, you would expect again that
such processes would not lead to a net
imbalance
of protons and antiprotons.
The key
is to say, "Wait a minute. How do I know
that
nature is truly symmetric
or truly
invariant under changing every particle
to every antiparticle?"
How do I know that this charge
conjugation is really a symmetry of
physics
and that everything that can happen can
happen with equal probability with
particles being replaced by
antiparticles?
And the answer is not only
do we not know that that's a symmetry,
we know that it's not a symmetry.
Experimental physics by now has
uncovered the fact that there is not an
exact symmetry
where you replace every particle by
antiparticle. That's been known for many
years now that there are slight
differences.
There are slight, small, residual
differences
in reaction rates, in probabilities,
when you replace particles by
antiparticles.
That
That conceivably could bias
one of these two relative to the other.
For example, this process could have a
slightly different probability than this
process.
This one being perhaps a little more
probable, this one a little less
probable. Then the bias would be towards
protons and electrons rather than
positrons and uh
All right. That means that we have to
also have a violation
of
charge conjugation
symmetry.
That there must be a bias in nature
which distinguishes particles from
antiparticles.
Indeed. Question. Yes. Couldn't it be
just be that there is a you know, just
I mean, even if they were
unbiased,
I mean, that they that sort of bias by
some kind of random process.
And just as you approach the the
the point of no return where you didn't
have to have that that reaction anymore,
you would have had some excess of one
over the other. Yeah, you might have had
some excess of some over one over the
other here, but over here, you would
have perhaps the opposite excess, and
over here, you would have But, still,
you might have had an overall excess.
Uh that would
on statistical grounds, you would expect
under those circumstances, Assuming
there was a symmetry, you would expect
the excess to be of order the square
root of the number of particles. This is
usual square root of n statistics.
All right?
There is something like about 10 to the
80th protons in the universe. Square
root of n is only 10 to the 40th and
that's
Sorry,
no, no, go back. Go back. Go back. Go
back.
If I take all of the particles in the
universe, known universe, there's
something like about 10 to the 90th.
That includes photons.
All right? The square root of that is
only 10 to the 45. So, that could
account for an imbalance of 10 to the 45
protons, but there's more like 10 to the
80th protons in the universe. So,
it's a very good question. How do I know
that it isn't statistical statistical
fluctuation,
but it's way beyond
uh statistics.
Yeah. The numbers just don't support
that. So, that's a very good question.
I thought of it myself years ago and
dismissed it very quickly.
Okay.
Uh well, yeah, yeah, but you might still
expect maybe the patchiness washed
itself out and
you know,
it's thinkable, but the numbers are too
far from from that. Now, the last thing
is a more subtle thing.
There is a symmetry of physics
which is not charge conjugation
symmetry, but it's a combination of
charge
conjugation
and time reversal.
Where
if you simultaneously
replace every particle by its
anti-particle and at the same time run
things backward in time,
then
that is an exact symmetry of nature.
You can ask me how we know that. Let me
just say that that is very deeply and
fundamentally built into the rules of
relativistic quantum mechanics,
relativistic quantum field theory. I'm
not going to try to explain it now. It's
called the CPT theorem.
You can look it up. The CPT theorem.
And unlike the charge conjugation
statement,
that's a thing which could be wrong.
Empirically, it's close to being
correct, but doesn't have to be correct.
The CPT theorem
is a theorem. It's a mathematical
theorem about relativity and quantum
mechanics.
And what it says,
as I said,
is if you take every particle and
replace it by its anti-particle and at
the same time run time backward. In
other words, take a movie of the
universe or movie of something run
backward,
then
that's an exact symmetry of nature.
Now, if I were to take a pot of hot gas
that had been sitting forever and ever
and ever for a long time and has come to
equilibrium and it's just sitting there,
so that nothing is going in one
direction or the other direction, that
means a movie of it run backward and
forward is exactly the same. It's in
equilibrium.
But if there's a symmetry that says that
if you let time
run backward and also interchange
particle with anti-particle,
but you're in a situation where it
doesn't matter whether you run time
backward or not because it looks exactly
the same,
then
you have a symmetry between particles
and anti-particles.
All right? So, the last condition in
order to break the symmetry between
particles and anti-particles
is that the universe at some point in
its history must have been sufficiently
out of equilibrium
so that
it definitely looked different going one
way than any other way. Now, you say,
"Of course the universe looks different
going one way than the other way."
All right?
Um
the universe is expanding. It's not
contracting. But on the other hand,
throughout most of the life of the
universe, it has been expanding so
slowly
that the expansion was negligible
on time scales of elementary particle
reactions.
Today, the universe expands on scales of
a billion years. Particle reactions,
which are the things that are relevant
here,
you know, 10 to the minus 25 seconds or
whatever.
Very, very rapid.
And so, the very slow expansion of the
universe, you can just think of that as
the pot sitting there forever.
And for most of the history of the
universe, it has been expanding very
slowly compared
to the particle physics rates.
Uh
nevertheless, sufficiently early in the
universe, sufficiently early, the
universe was certainly out of
equilibrium. Sufficiently early, it
explosively expanded.
And during that period of time,
it looked different from a from the
microscopic point of view, from the
individual point of view of particle
collisions and so forth,
the expansion of the universe
was very, very significant and the
universe did not look symmetric going
forward and backward. And it's during
that time, it's called the third
condition is called
being out of equilibrium.
Now, it's an interesting theorem
that if all of these conditions are
satisfied, number one,
that baryon number is not conserved,
number two,
that the symmetry between particles and
anti-particles
is broken, is not a symmetry. And third,
that the universe was for some period
out of equilibrium. In other words, that
the expansion rate was fast enough to
affect particle reactions,
then
even if you start with a universe which
is equal number of protons and
anti-protons, equal number of positrons
and anti-positrons,
it will get tilted one way or the other.
It's essentially a theorem
that uh as I said, it was discovered by
Sakharov 1967.
And
Andrei Sakharov, that is.
And um
is called the theory of baryogenesis.
The part of it that we don't know with
certainty, this we know. The universe,
well,
we can conjecture that the universe at
the very beginning
at the very earliest times was I just a
second. Was expanding rapidly enough
that it affected particle collisions.
This is very reasonable.
This is known to be true.
The violation of baryon number is the
question mark.
We have never seen a reaction in nature
where the number of protons minus anti
And now, when I say protons, I mean
protons plus neutrons.
Protons plus neutrons
minus anti-protons minus anti-neutrons.
We have never seen a reaction in nature
which violates this here.
That may simply be because we've never
had enough energy to create reactions
that do that.
All right? So, this is the question mark
here.
If it turns out that baryon number is
not conserved, then it's essentially a
theorem that there will be a little bit
left over
one sign or the other,
protons or anti-protons.
Uh when people make models of this
and they start calculating,
they get numbers not so different than
one part in in a billion. So, the one
part in a billion is not an unreasonable
answer.
But we we simply don't really have a
theory that goes back that far. And so,
at the present time,
this is conjectural that the universe
started out neutral,
neutral with respect to this baryon
number,
and then in the process of cooling as it
went out of equilibrium, as it expanded
very rapidly,
these other conditions being satisfied
tilted it a little bit
one part in a billion
to protons versus anti-protons, one part
in a billion to electrons versus
positrons.
And then in the process of cooling down
beyond that,
every excess anti-proton, every
anti-proton
found a proton, annihilated with it, and
only left over this one in a billion.
Same thing with the electrons and
positrons. And today, what we have is
that tiny fossil remnant of the uh
uh
the universe looks like it's very, very
grossly
matter and not anti-matter,
but it's a simple remnant of something
which was much, much more equal at the
early times. So, that's an interesting
story. Well, Michael had a question.
Yeah.
Matching up the CPT to the 1 2 3, you're
saying numbers two and three are
C violation and Okay. Let me let me
clar- let me be more exact. I just
called this charge conjugation where you
replace a particle by its antiparticle.
Um
There's
It's really something called C times P.
Where P is called parity and it means
space
Yeah, CP violation.
We could call this
charge conjugate CP violation. CP.
But it is replacing particles by
antiparticles and at the same time
hmm?
Say it again.
This? Yeah.
That's No, that's time reversal. Yeah,
time reversal. Yeah, time reversal,
right. Okay, and then number one is
neither none of them. Well, one of
number one is just something completely
different.
Now, I should say there's very strong
reason
to believe that baryon number is not a
good real genuine conservation law of
physics.
Uh
There are many reasons, but however, it
has never been detected
the violation of baryon number.
Disappointing fact that though yeah. How
close are you to the Big Bang?
Very close.
Well, it's
Look, it it it's a question of
definition of what you mean by the Big
Bang.
There may have been a long period
of inflation
which preceded what we normally think of
as the Big Bang. But what we normally
think of as the Big Bang, we're pretty
close to the Big Bang.
What are your estimates for what energy
levels you would see the violation of
baryon conservation? Where you would see
it significantly, yeah.
And then how many orders of magnitude
beyond what LHC can do?
13.
No, no, no. You see okay
No, it
it's more complicated than that. Um
All right.
Supposing there was some reaction
which became important at high
temperatures
which really became highly probable at
high temperatures
which allowed
some collision to take place which would
change the number of protons and so
forth.
It might nevertheless be even though you
don't have that much energy around
that a process can still happen, but
with very very small probability.
Extremely small. Now, that's typical.
Um
That's a typical kind of thing where
something can become strong and
important when you have a lot of energy
and that doesn't mean that it's
impossible at low energy. It just means
it becomes very very improbable.
So
if it's true that there are reactions in
nature which violate this baryon number
uh but only significantly
with a high probability when the
temperature is really high, here would
be a process for example
a proton
becoming a positron
and a photon.
That's a perfectly good. But you might
it might only happen when the proton
let's say not only happen. It might
mostly happen when the proton collides
with something else at very high energy
that shakes it up a lot and then kicks
off this collision.
Well, it would still be in most theories
that it could happen even at low
temperature and low energy, but with a
very very diminished probability.
Um how diminished?
Well, we know something about the
lifetime of a proton.
The lifetime of a proton how how long
must the proton last?
Well, ordinary particle physics
reactions happen very fast in terribly
small fractions of a second.
So just applying ordinary dimensional
analysis to this, you might expect that
this would happen in a terribly tiny
fraction of a second, but it doesn't. It
certainly doesn't. Your protons don't
disappear spontaneously like that.
Um and turn into positrons. How long
What's the minimum lifetime of a proton?
Well, I can tell you this that the
proton basically have to last the age of
the universe for sure.
Okay, for sure they must last the age of
the universe cuz they're still around.
Uh so at least 10 billion years.
But in fact the age the lifetime of a
proton is much much longer than that.
The reason is because if the lifetime of
the proton was about 10 billion years,
then if you took 10 billion protons,
which is not very many
then one of them on the average would
decay in 1 year.
If the average if the half-life of the
proton was 10 billion years
then in 1 year
if you had 10 billion protons to start
with, one of the protons would decay.
Now, it's easy to see
uh and and then if you had a large
number of protons, you know, 10 to the
23rd protons, you would have a lot of
reactions of this type taking place even
though
the likelihood that any proton decayed
would be very very small. So we know
that the lifetime is much much longer
than the age of the universe.
In fact
it was known
many years ago to be upwards somewheres
around more than 10 to the 27 years.
That's a very very long time. Much much
longer than the age of the universe.
Starting sometime in the late 70s,
people started to build very big
experiments
where they would take very large
quantities of material which usually
meant water. In fact, it always meant
water.
Why water? Cuz water is transparent and
you can look through it and see the
light. This incidentally would also this
produces a photon for example.
Photons are light. You want transparent
materials. Um
water is good. Take huge quantities of
water.
Huge means you know, many many swimming
pools, hundreds of swimming pools and
sit and watch the many many protons and
wait for one proton to decay. Can you
see one proton to decay in a big pool of
water? Yes, you can.
You have many many light detectors. So
you have a great big pool of water.
Photodetectors all along the sides here.
And if a proton decays, it emits photons
and you can detect it. So you can detect
one reaction
in a great big huge pool
of very transparent water.
There are all kinds of background noise.
So you bury the process deep under the
earth in a mine somewheres where cosmic
rays get cetera et cetera.
And it was fully expected
that with 10 to the 32 protons, you
would see one of them decay in about a
year in a in a year's time. Nothing
happened.
So we now know that the lifetime of the
proton is longer than something like
about 10 to the 34 years.
Uh
that's a long time for the proton to
last. But what we don't know
and what we won't know for many years is
that when collisions happen
that really excite the proton, that pump
a lot of energy in, that this process
doesn't happen very readily. There are
many processes in nature, many things in
nature
which are very very improbable unless
you have a large energy to excite them.
And proton change or violation of baryon
number could well be one of those things
that it just takes a very high
temperature to precipitate.
Uh and that's what we don't know.
This is still a question mark.
Question? Yeah. Um you
the
the baryon conservation describes why if
positive baryon, negative baryon,
whatever.
Um
but since the universe is electrically
neutral
um
what guarantees that there's the same
number of protons as electrons?
Well, the basic elementary particle
physics processes
for deep mathematical reasons that we
don't need to go into here, always
conserve the basic processes of nature
uh such as elementary particle processes
always conserve the electric charge. So
roughly speaking
this is a process where the electric
charge hops from the proton to the
electron, but electric charge can't
disappear. So what guarantees it?
Um
Maxwell's equations
uh fundamental symmetries of physics.
No, no, no.
No, I mean like okay, there's the same
number of in the in the the soup,
there's the same number of
uh protons as antiprotons, positrons as
electrons. Right.
But as the universe cooled, you know,
the antiparticles disappear, but the
universe is still electrically neutral.
Right.
So That is what in fact happens.
Yeah.
But it's another question to ask why it
got biased towards protons instead of
antiprotons. No, my question is why is
the same number of electrons and
protons? So it's electrically neutral.
Those That's because the basic processes
of physics, whenever a proton
disappears, another charged particle has
to reappear.
So it can't get out of balance
electrically.
Uh where in this picture does uh
if we
if we keep watching it fall back, where
do we unfreeze out
the photonic degrees of freedom and
reabsorb
Which degrees of freedom?
Photonic.
What does it mean to unfreeze photonic
degrees of freedom? Well, if we suppose
the photon arises from spontaneous
symmetry breakdown
of the local
Oh, oh, oh, oh, of um of the standard
model.
Yeah. Uh that happens
at an energy
of about 100 GeV
or 200 maybe 250 GeV.
Uh
It's not that the photon disappears.
It's that uh the weak interactions uh
become much much more like the
electromagnetic interactions. The weak
interactions meaning uh those things
involving neutrinos and so forth.
So,
the symmetry breaking which made the
photon special
relative to the Z boson and the W boson
and so forth, that happened
um at a temperature
about 100 times or 200 times larger
than the energy at which protons and
antiprotons first were formed in the But
that's that's that's known physics.
That's known physics.
That we know where that happened.
And it doesn't It plays a role, but it
doesn't play a dramatic role in this
story here.
Yeah. Does dark
How does dark matter modify this picture
anyway? Not particularly. Um
dark matter itself
you can ask whether dark matter is
anything like
it's not protons, but whether it has its
own conservation laws
which had to be broken in similar ways
to get a net amount of dark matter.
Probably not. The The dark matter
doesn't influence this particular
question in any in any special way.
be hanging around there
It was hanging around. In the very early
part of the picture. Yeah. Even at very
high temperature. It was there. Right.
But
in most theories of dark matter, the
dark matter
doesn't interact very much with ordinary
matter.
And so, it was more or less spectator.
No.
Could Could it somehow been involved
It's possible. It's possible. In the
very high It's possible.
It's possible, but I don't think it
would change the basic principles.
Wouldn't change the basic principles.
Yeah.
Condition number three is equivalent to
violation of CPT symmetry. No. No, no,
no.
Well, yes and no.
Um
See Let's just take T. Forget the CP,
just T.
T is time reversal symmetry.
All right?
It means anything that can happen one
way
can also happen if you ran things the
opposite way.
But it doesn't say that the actual
history of the universe
was symmetric. It just says whatever the
history of the universe is
if it can go one way
it can also go the other way.
All right? Now, all that this is says is
that the universe was out of out of
equilibrium, which means that it wasn't
static, that it wasn't just sitting
there
like a
uh like a pot of stew
uh untouched. It was changing. The pot
was expanding.
A
uh a violation of CPT symmetry
would mean
that running the film backward was not a
possible solution of the equations of
physics. And that's that's that's that's
something This is This is um
Let's put it this way.
To violate this, we would have to
violate something very deep about
quantum field theory and special
relativity and quantum mechanics.
So, while
I don't think any of us can say never
that that that that that that CPT
violation is not a possibility.
It's not a possibility within the
current mathematics of quantum field
theory. So, this This is considered
pretty sacred generally.
It doesn't mean that the universe can
isn't going one way. It just means if
it's going one way and you run it
backward, that's also a possible a
possible world.
Right?
Right.
For example, I mean
I am right-handed.
Okay?
Does that mean that there's a left-right
asymmetry in nature? No, it just means
that
another
creature could exist, doesn't
necessarily have to exist. But another
creature could exist who was
left-handed.
And be otherwise exactly like me. It
doesn't mean that I'm necessarily
ambidextrous.
It means that whatever I am,
the reflection could exist.
Same thing about time reversal here.
Uh whatever the universe is doing
it's a consistent
a set of uh solutions of equations of
the theory to run backward. With with
the other change the changes in parity
Yeah, with the other changes
simultaneously alongside. That's right.
Yeah. Yeah. How does gravity affect all
this? Well,
gravity, of course, is deeply connected
with the expansion of the universe.
But
other than that
Okay, I I Let Let me give you a um yeah,
let me tell you one of the reasons
that we have a fairly strong belief
that this conservation of baryon number
cannot be an exact uh conservation law
of physics. And it does involve gravity.
Before I say that, let me say that the
gravitational interactions between
particles are so negligible
at least at the any reasonable energies
that it really doesn't play much role in
this.
But there's a logical point which is
interesting.
And it has to do with black holes of all
things.
Um imagine a black hole being formed out
of the material of a star.
I forget how many protons number or what
the baryon number of a star is, but
something like about 10 to the 60th if I
remember.
Something like about 10 to the 60th
protons in a star.
It has a net baryon number which is
large and positive.
Now, the star collapses to a black hole.
It runs out of fuel, collapses, and
becomes a black hole.
Well, the black hole may have all of
those protons inside it somewheres,
but then at least according to theory,
if you wait long enough, the black hole
will start to evaporate.
It will evaporate and into photons.
Basically photons.
The temperature of a large black hole is
very very low, and it's nowhere's near
enough energy for it to be able to
create protons. So, this large black
hole, which started out as 10 to the
60th protons, contracted, became a black
hole, and started to emit ordinary
blackbody radiation.
Slowly it heated up, but by the time it
heated up enough to be able to create
protons, it was as tiny as a um
Well, it was a very very small.
Very few protons left to be able to be
emitted. So, we know from black hole
physics and the evaporation of black
holes at some level
at some level
the conservation of the number of
protons in the world must be violated.
That's something that
that most physicists believe. But that's
about the only way that I can think that
the two ways that that gravity comes
into the story.
One is
that that it strongly suggests
violation of conservation of baryon
number because of this black hole story.
The second way that it comes in is it
has to do with the expansion of the
universe. If it wasn't for gravity
and Einstein's equations and so forth
there would be no expansion. And without
expansion of the universe, there would
be no out of equilibrium.
So, the expansion of the universe, which
is a gravitational phenomenon
is part of the out of equilibrium. But
apart from that
gravity doesn't play any significant
role in this. Yeah. And if we had a
black hole that was charged Yeah.
wouldn't that same argument show
No. just violation of charge? That's a
very good question, but the answer is
no.
And the reason
is
because
charged black holes, like any other
charges, have electric lines of flux
coming out of them.
And that electric those electric lines
of flux
are sort of tied down at infinity.
And they keep track
of the electric charge of the black
hole.
Um
Electrically charged black holes will
not completely evaporate.
They will evaporate photons, losing
energy, until they get down to some
minimum energy called the extremal
energy of the extremal black hole. And
then they'll just sit there and stop
evaporating.
And uh black holes which have stopped
evaporating because
they have electric charge are called
extremal. They're extremal in that they
have that their mass is the extreme
lower end of a charged black hole. So,
no, charged black holes don't
indefinitely evaporate.
Yeah. There's also the confusion when
people talk about Big Bang and and black
hole and the and the density. If you If
you think of a a volume of that great
dense soup, uh
you would calculate that the the radius
of a black
that that radius of a black it would
collapse into a black black hole based
on its density and its size. I mean,
this this this quark soup that you were
talking about is is is much I got a much
denser density than a neutron
star and and the mass is much greater
than what's expanding.
So, that's that's because space is
expanding. It will expand Well, I don't
know. It it is expanding because All
right, is it because space is expanding
or just because it is expanding?
Uh
No, it doesn't collapse into a black
hole or
instead, it does something else. It
expands.
Um
Mhm. So,
No, there's no issue. There's no issue
of all this dense material somehow
forming a black hole. That's that's not
an issue.
Uh
The black hole idea that I just
expressed was a thought experiment. It's
a thought experiment to try to convince
yourself that the laws of physics as we
now know them sort of force the issue
here. That the conservation of baryon
number is
uh not something that will persist
indefinitely in physics.
By now, there are so many reasons
to believe
uh in the violation of baryon number
that that it's it's
it's
uh it's a half a a half a check.
At at least half a check.
Would one know how to amend the uh
the standard model in order to include
those reactions?
The trouble is the opposite. Almost any
way that you try to amend the standard
model
winds up making the lifetime of the
proton too fast.
Yeah. So, yeah, it's real easy to uh
to make a make it run to make it to make
it too much. It's hard to keep it uh the
proton stable as it is.
Can Can a proton
uh
proton absorb a photon and reach a
higher
energy level with the quarks inside of
it?
All right. Say it again. Can a proton
Can a proton absorb a photon?
A proton can absorb a photon.
And it will get excited.
The quarks uh The quarks will start to
get excited. They will get very excited.
Um
But, of course,
the first thing will happen
is they'll spit out more quarks, but the
quarks and anti-quarks, mesons.
Mesons maybe they'll vibrate and spit
out some mesons.
Um
To the best of our knowledge,
the amount of energy that you would have
to shove into a proton
to make it decay and disappear, leaving
only a positron,
would have to be enormously large simply
because the proton is known to be so
stable.
Known to be so stable
and therefore this must be a very remote
and unlikely process.
Uh-huh.
The only way to make it unlikely is to
push it to very very high energy and
um
So, we could talk more about it, but uh
Yeah. Um before we we discuss
the question about square root of n
statistics
to speak louder. Um
we talked about square root of n
statistics before. Um
With square root of n Square root of n,
yeah. Right. Um
Well, um
earlier, was the number of particles
nearly constant or is it possible that
at some early time
Yeah.
Yeah. Um
Some of this is theory, some of it is
observation.
And I'm not going to try to distinguish
now.
But,
roughly speaking, the number of
particles in the universe did not change
from some very early time.
Uh the number of particles
within a certain coordinate patch within
a coordinate patch.
And the the correct statement, the exact
statement,
is that in a
universe in equilibrium or just close to
equilibrium, an an
adiabatically expanding universe,
adiabatically expanding means that the
rate of expansion is much slower than
any fundamental particle process or any
fundamental process in nature.
What did you ask me? I lost track.
Well, just if the number of particles
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. In an
adiabatic process, which means a slow
process,
entropy is conserved. Entropy doesn't
change in an adiabatic process. Now, if
you take a gas or a soup of elementary
particles and you calculate the entropy,
it is
within a factor of two or pi or some
numerical number, it's the number of
particles.
So, in an adiabatic process where the
universe is expanding
slower than particle reactions are
taking place,
even though particle reactions can take
place,
and they do take place, and they might
even be biased in one direction or
another,
the net number of particles tends not to
change. And if it does change, it
changes maybe over the whole history of
the universe by a factor of 10 or
something like that, not by an enormous
amount.
So,
uh
Originally, the the early questions
about the subject had the whole story
upside down.
Instead of asking why there were so few
protons relative to photons,
the question was asked the other way.
Why are there so many photons relative
to the number of protons? And the idea
was that there must have been something
in the physics which just
proliferated huge numbers of photons
and increased the entropy of the
universe. Where did all this entropy
come from?
So, it was thought that what was what we
needed was an explanation of some kind
of process which just created wholesale
enormous amounts of entropy out of
uh
out of organized energy, out of energy
which was organized.
Eventually, the question got turned
around the other way. There's a certain
amount of entropy in the world. That
entropy has not changed very much, but
somehow the protons and antiprotons
disappeared, became photons, and left
over only this very very small fraction.
So, the emphasis changed from trying to
explain the production of entropy,
the production of uh photons from from
nothing, basically,
to a the question of why in the early
universe the imbalance between particles
and antiparticles was so small.
Uh Nobody ever found a way to create all
that entropy
uh
through the expansion of the universe.
Though, all that entropy means this very
large number of photons.
So, nobody believes now that the problem
is how do you create entropy? Everybody
believes the problem is
uh
Well,
the problem at the moment
is verifying
in the in the laboratory or otherwise
that there's a violation of baryon
number.
And that'll probably happen sooner or
later.
Leave in these big experiments involving
these huge uh quantities of water.
Um
Wait 100 years and uh
a proton might decay.
That's the sort of estimate that's out
there now. Wait 100 years and one proton
will decay.
Hm? Make sure you're looking at that
time.
Yeah, that's the question. I mean, you
got to run these experiments for a long
period of time. Who's going to pay for
them?
It's going to be tough on the graduate
students.
What happens if What happens if it
decays while the graduate student is
asleep?
Okay.
More questions. Good.
Yeah.
Um neutrons will decay into a proton
electron. Right. And neutrino.
And neutrino, antineutrino. Uh I'm
wondering how the neutrons uh
persisted beyond the 15-minute half-life
if there are any left in the universe
Yeah. after that time. All right. Cool.
A free neutron will decay in 15 12
minutes. I forget what their number is.
12 minutes, something like that.
A free neutron
A neutron, incidentally,
also has baryon number, same as a
proton.
So, here's an example of a process
which does not violate baryon number.
It's called beta decay. A neutron
A neutron becomes a proton,
an electron,
E minus.
So far, it's a perfectly good process.
An electrically neutral particle becomes
a plus charge and a minus charge.
And also, at the same time, an
antineutrino is emitted.
Antineutrino is emitted. That for
technical reasons, the antineutrino has
to be there.
This is a process, and it does happen.
All neutrons, sooner or later, decay
like this.
And they last about 12 minutes now
before they decay. That's the half-life.
Maybe it's 15. I remember 12, but uh
It's a interesting question why they
last so long. Elementary particle
processes are usually measured in
you know, very, very small time periods.
Why does a neutron last so long? And the
answer
is a combination of answers, but
um
one of the elements that goes in is that
the sum of the mass of the proton, the
positron, and the neutrino is almost
exactly or very close to the mass of the
neutron.
So, that means if if these particles
were a little bit heavier,
there wouldn't be enough energy for the
neutron to decay.
So, if the proton was just a little tiny
bit heavier,
the neutron could not decay at all
because there wouldn't be enough energy
for it to make a proton, an electron,
and a neutrino.
It just so happens that the neutron is
almost equal
is only a tiny bit heavier than the
proton,
and just a teeny, teeny bit heavier than
the proton plus the electron. So, there
isn't much energy there.
And for that reason, the process takes a
long time to happen.
Uh but, yes, the the neutron decays in
That's a neutron
a free neutron. Now, if a neutron is
bound in a nucleus,
it may have some binding energy. Let's
put it into a nucleus with a bunch with
some protons. Let's say with a with a
with another with a proton.
Then there's some binding energy.
There's some nuclear binding energy, and
the energy of the neutron and the proton
is not the sum
or is not them The mass is not the sum
of the neutron plus the proton, but it's
the neutron plus the proton minus the
binding energy.
Right?
Here you might say, "Why doesn't this
happen? The proton just go off, and the
neutron
decay?" And the answer is that there
wasn't enough energy to begin with.
Because there was all of this negative
binding energy,
which was enough The negative The
binding energy of nuclei is very small.
It's not very big.
But, the available energy was small to
begin with. So, the neutron, when it
binds to the proton,
becomes stable because it just doesn't
have enough energy to decay.
So,
are neutrons created, or are the number
of neutrons in the universe constantly
decreasing?
Decreasing?
Yeah, it's probably constantly
decreasing. Um
But, uh
Yeah, if a neutron gets knocked out of a
nucleus somehow,
then it will decay.
It
So, for example,
cosmic rays don't have neutrons in them.
Why don't they have neutrons in them?
Because the neutron decays before. What
does it become? It becomes a proton and
an electron and so forth.
So, yeah, I guess I guess it's probably
fair to say the number of neutrons is
decreasing. Where do they come from?
Nuclei.
But, I mean, after the Big Bang? Well,
actually, I take it back. I take it
back. There is a source of creation of
neutrons, and it's a big source of
creation. It's neutron stars.
Neutron stars.
Um
When a star collapses, it can become
very dense, and uh
Well, hydrogen burns into helium in the
in the in the sun.
There's nuclear reactions which
Yeah, yeah. There are nuclear reactions
which
Right. Yeah. I take it back. It's
probably not true that the number of
neutrons is decreasing. Probably
increasing because of what you say.
Yeah.
Um
Okay. If we're finished, uh